Finding Aid for Women in Engineering Office (University of Michigan) records, 1990-2000
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Women in Engineering Office (University of Michigan) records
1990-2000
University of Michigan. Women in Engineering Office.
033 Bimu 2
Office within the College of Engineering devoted to providing services and resources to support women in engineering programs. Include topical files on issues facing women engineers, projects and programs supported by the office such as the Marian Sarah Parker Scholarship program, workshop material and documentation from the Graduate Experience Project. Some scattered photographs are also included.
1 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group (donor no. 8994 ) was received from the unit in several accessions: July 2000, January and May 2002.
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The Vice President and Chief Financial Officer records are open for research except for certain records restricted by statute or university policy. Restricted material includes personnel-related files, including search, review, promotion, and tenure files; student educational records; client/patient records; and records of executive officers of the university.
The Women in Engineering Office (WIE) at the College of Engineering serves women students and faculty through its programs, services and resources. It aims to increase the number of qualified women in the field of engineering, create a supportive environment and make available information about relevant women's issues.
WIE originated from the College of Engineering's Pilot Women's Program, established in 1991 under the guidance of Michael Parson, Associate Dean for Undergraduate Education, and coordinated by a recent graduate of the College of Engineering, Gina Sartor. The Pilot Women's Program represented a collaboration with the Women in Science Program (now Women in Science and Engineering) and implemented programs similar to theirs and those at other institutions for engineering students at the University of Michigan. WIE served as an advocate for students and as a liaison to student organizations on campus such as the Society of Women Engineers (SWE) and Women in Graduate Engineering Sciences (WINGES), and to other university offices such as University of Michigan Engineering Council (UMEC). In addition to supporting current students at the college, the program also organized activities for young girls and high school students with interests in math and science.
One of the program's primary activities was, and continues to be, administering the Marian Sarah Parker Scholars Program (originally called the "Pipeline Project"), named in honor of the first woman to graduate from the College of Engineering. The program, originally funded by a National Science Foundation grant, was intended to encourage undergraduate women to pursue advanced degrees in engineering through panel discussions, seminars, group activities and an opportunity to conduct research.
In 1995, along with the Women in Science and Engineering Program, Rackham School of Graduate Studies, the College of Engineering, and others, WIE supported the Graduate Experience Project, a "comprehensive, university-wide initiative to recruit and retain women graduate students in engineering, physics and chemistry." The project focused on three areas: programs (such as orientation for new graduate students, peer advising, workshops and research fellowships), institutional change (through faculty/staff training and the establishment of best practices) and research (including faculty surveys and focus groups).
For current information, refer to the WIE website, available as of October 2002 at http://www.engin.umich.edu/students/support/wie/index.htm.
The WIE records document the programs that the office supported and helped to organize. The records include topical files on issues facing women engineers, projects and programs supported by the office such as the Marian Sarah Parker Scholarship program, workshop material and documentation from the Graduate Experience Project. Some scattered photographs are also included. The records (1 linear foot) date from 1990-2000 and are arranged in two series: Programming and Topical Files.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. Women in Engineering Office.; Women in engineering.; Women engineers.; Women college students--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan. College of Engineering.; University of Michigan--Students--Scholarships, fellowships, etc.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Programming, 1990-1999
  The Programming series, 1990-1999 (.8 linear feet), contains documents of two of the office's programs. The Graduate Experience Project files provide information about the grant that funded the project and programs offered to students, including peer advising and research through the Sloan Summer Fellowship Program. Records of the Marian Sarah Parker Scholars Program for undergraduate students include similar material about workshops and internships. Researchers can learn from fellowship and internship files the kinds of research projects these programs supported.
  - Graduate Experience Project
    - Sloan Grant, 1994-1995 (Box 1)
    - Peer advising program (Box 1)
    - Sloan Summer Fellowship Program, 1996-1999 (Box 1)
    - Welcome event, 1996-1997 (Box 1)
    - Prospective students, 1996 (Box 1)
    - New graduate students, 1996 (Box 1)
    - Women graduate students by department, 1996 (Box 1)
    - Peer advisors, 1996 (Box 1)
    - Sloan Summer Fellowship, 1996 (Box 1)
    - Sloan Summer Fellowship, 1997 (Box 1)
    - Cross-fertilization program, 1997-1998 (Box 1)
    - Cross-fertilization program, 1998-1999 (Box 1)
    - Working file, 1998-1999 (Box 1)
    - Welcome letter, 1998 (Box 1)
    - Welcome dinner, 1998 (Box 1)
    - Peer advisor training, 1998 (Box 1)
    - Peer advising, 1998 (Box 1)
    - Sloan Summer Fellowship, 1998 (Box 1)
    - "Yes" letters, 1998; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - "No" letters, 1998 (Box 1)
    - New graduate students, 1999 (Box 1)
    - Welcome letter, 1999 (Box 1)
    - Welcome dinner, 1999 (Box 1)
    - Sloan Summer Fellowship, 1999 (Box 1)
    - "Yes" letters, 1999 (Box 1)
    - "No" letters, 1999 (Box 1)
  - Marian Sarah Parker Scholars Program (MSP)
    - General, 1991-1992 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 1992-1995 (Box 1)
    - Course credit, 1992-1993 (Box 1)
    - Evaluations, 1992 (Box 1)
    - Saturday seminar, 1992-1993 (Box 1)
    - Advisory meeting, 1991-1993 (Box 1)
    - Payroll, 1992 (Box 1)
    - Planning Your Future, 1992-1993 (Box 1)
    - Scholars, 1991-1993 (Box 1)
    - Moms in Science, 1992-1993 (Box 1)
    - Invitation, 1990-1992 (Box 1)
    - Reception, 1993 (Box 1)
    - 1994-1996 (Box 1)
    - General, 1994-1995 (Box 1)
    - Faculty mentors, 1994-1995 (Box 1)
    - Spring/summer interns, 1994-1995 (Box 1)
    - Fall interns, 1995-1996 (Box 1)
    - General, 1996 (Box 1)
    - Awards, 1996 (Box 1)
    - Mentor query, 1996 (Box 1)
    - Internship reports, 1996 (Box 1)
    - General, 1997 (Box 1)
    - Awards, 1997 (Box 1)
    - Mentor query, 1997 (Box 1)
    - Internships, 1997 (Box 1)
    - Internship reports, 1997; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - General, 1998 (Box 1)
      (includes photographs)
    - Awards, 1998 (Box 1)
    - Mentor query, 1998 (Box 1)
    - Internships, 1998 (Box 1)
    - Internship reports, 1998 (Box 1)
- Topical Files, 1990-2000
  The Topical Files series, 1990-2000 (0.2 linear feet), is an alphabetically arranged sequence containing correspondence and information about some of the smaller programs with which WIE was involved. Researchers can also gain insight into the origins of the office through descriptions of the Pipeline Proposal and evaluation of the Pilot Women's Program at the end of its first year.
  - Admissions, 1992 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1990 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1994 (Box 1)
  - Engineering Summer Symposium for Seniors (ES3), 1990-1991 (Box 1)
  - Graduate women, 1991-1992 (Box 1)
  - Marie Curie Exhibition, 2000; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Minority Engineering Program Office (MEPO), 1991 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous activities, 1991-1992 (Box 1)
    (includes Year-End Report)
  - Pipeline Proposal, 1990-1993 (Box 1)
  - Resource people, 1991-1992 (Box 1)
  - Single parents, 1994-1995 (Box 1)
  - Statistics, 1991-1992 (Box 1)
  - Summer Science for Girls Program, 1992 (Box 1)